<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to the members of Parliament for the county of [blank] concerning the Triennial bill. Wherein is considered, what may be the easiest way to secure Triennial Parliaments, without intruding upon the prerogative. With some objections to the methods of that kind, that formerly have been enacted into law. / By some electors of members of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Some electors of members of Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1743B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52614751</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52614751</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175943</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04012)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175943)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2755:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to the members of Parliament for the county of [blank] concerning the Triennial bill. Wherein is considered, what may be the easiest way to secure Triennial Parliaments, without intruding upon the prerogative. With some objections to the methods of that kind, that formerly have been enacted into law. / By some electors of members of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Some electors of members of Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Text in double columns.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Rules and practice --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175943:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->
            <head>A LETTER To the Members of Parliament For the County of....... Concerning the Triennial Bill.</head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein is conſidered, what may be the eaſieſt Way to ſecure Triennial Parliaments, without intruding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Prerogative. With ſome Objections to the Methods of that Kind, that formerly have been enacted into Laws.</head>
            <byline>By ſome Electors of Members of Parliament.</byline>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Triennial Bill has been the Subject of much Diſcourſe: Wherein we the Electors of divers Members of Parliament do appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend theſe following Points.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That a bare poſitive Law for ſettled and certain Parliaments, without any Means to induce or procure an Execution of it, will be an ineffectual Law: For if Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhould not be called accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175943:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->to ſuch a Law, what Remedy could there be had for the nonexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution without Violence?</p>
            <p n="2">2. That to lodg or place any executive Power for the Calling of Parliaments in any other Perſon or Perſons, or in any other manner than as now is uſed by the King himſelf, ſeems to tend too much to the Diminution of the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Royal, and the Encouragement of thoſe who are of the Republi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Principle, as was evident in the Statute of 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. herein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after mentioned, which we ſubmit to your Conſideration.</p>
            <p>Therefore to go ſuch a middle Way to attain the End of frequent and certain Parliaments, as ſhall not touch, infringe or diminiſh the Prerogative of Calling, Proroguing and Diſſolving Parliaments, and yet ſhall anſwer the Subjects Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, recommends it ſelf to all lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Peace and Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween King and Parliament; and that is, to annex the following Condition (or ſomewhat to the like Effect) to the next Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, which ſhall renew the Grant to the King of the Cuſtoms of Tonnage and Poundage, Exciſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is now expiring, (that is to ſay)</p>
            <p>
               <q>That in caſe there ſhall not from henceforth be a Parliament called and held once in every <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap> Years, to be accounted from the End of the next preceding Seſſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; which ſhall be permitted to ſit the ſpace of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap> Days at the leaſt after the meeting thereof. And if ſuch Parliament be not (in the Interval thereof) Diſſolved once in every <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap> Years, from the making hereof, and a new Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment called, which ſhall ſit within the Times, and in manner as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; Then and in any of the Caſes aforeſaid, this preſent Act, and all and every the Paiments and Revenues therein granted ſhall ceaſe and be void.</q>
            </p>
            <p>A Clauſe may be likewiſe added to make it Criminal to pay the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms and Exciſe after the Breach of that Condition.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Grant of the Revenue, with ſuch a Condition annexed, may be made temporary for nine or twelve Years: And by ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationary Law, the Conveniences and Inconveniences thereof may in ſuch a Time be diſcerned.</p>
            <p>That ſuch a Law will be effectual and proper for the deſigned End, appears,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that it is conſiſtent and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable with the Political Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Kingdom, for it leaves the Prerogative to call Parliaments intire and untouch'd.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's natural to the Act it ſelf, for thoſe Revenues ariſe by the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175943:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->Grant of the Commons, and may be defeated by a Condition.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It will be ſufficiently remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, becauſe the Subject may eaſily take advantage of the Breach of the Condition, by non-paiment of the Cuſtoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without acting any thing to the prejudice of the Prerogative.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is operative enough to the deſigned End, for the Ceſſer of thoſe Revenues, will be more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive to call Parliaments than any other Reaſon whatſoever. And,</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is moſt reaſonable; For the Deſign of granting thoſe Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, was to ſupport the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Good of the Subject: But it's apparent that the neglect of Parliaments formerly did high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſtruct the Good of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: Therefore by the uſing of thoſe Revenues for the enabling a Neglect of Parliaments, (as in the latter End of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second) the Deſign of granting them was avoided. And conſequently it is moſt reaſonable that upon ſuch a Uſer, the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues ſo granted ſhould ceaſe.</p>
            <p>The Methods that have been formerly taken to ſecure the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Calling of Parliaments, have hitherto proved wholly ineffectual: for the Statute of 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. which lodged a Power in the Lord Chancellor (in caſe of the King's Default) to call Parliaments; and if he failed, then in the Peers or any twelve of them; and if they failed, then in the Sheriffs; and if they failed, then in the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> introduced a kind of Republick into the Monarchy, by ſetting up a Supream Power be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Royal Power, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently inconſiſtent with it. And accordingly would be eaſily avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for if the King (as eaſily he might) ſhould have overawed the Chancellor, and ſhould have iſſued out a Proclamation to prohibit the Meeting of the Peers, What Peers would have ventured to have put this Act in Execution? Or how would the Sheriffs have agreed (all over the Nation) in one Mind to have made Elections? Or how would the Free-holders have been animated univerſally to Aſſemble and Elect? Or what Protection could the Members have had to meet? Or how could one Part of them have been aſſured that the reſt would have met at the Day?</p>
            <p>And the Statute of 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 2, <hi>cap.</hi> 1. which repeals this Act of 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. and yet ſeems to make Proviſion for Triennial Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, has been wholly uſeleſs, (tho yet in Force) becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175943:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->by is provided no Remedy to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Execution of it. And it's plain, that a bare Poſitive Law in this Caſe, without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding a Remedy for the Subject peaceably to procure the Execution of it, muſt needs be a fruitleſs Law.</p>
            <p>Whereas againſt the Acceptance of the Revenues, with the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Condition annexed, there can be no colour of Objection, for it neceſſitates no more than what by Law ought to be done: And what is endeavoured, ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved will be done; beſides it will be (in all probability) an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable Precedent; for it cannot be ſuppoſed that the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> after they have gained a kind of Certainty of Anniverſary Parliaments, will again abandon themſelves to the Uncertainty that in the former Reigns has been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſuppoſed Right that Electors have to communicate their Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions to their Repreſentatives in Parliament, and the ſeeming Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a Miſunderſtanding about the Triennial Bill, and likewiſe the impoſſibility of making this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition any other way, has procur'd You this Trouble from</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Electors.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
